<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "gnc-docbookx.dtd">

<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Version: 2.0.x
   Last modified: January 20th 2017
        modified: December 7th 2009
        modified: May 13th 2007
        modified: November 28th 2006
        modified: August 12th 2006
  modified: February 28th 2005

  Maintainers:
               Alex Aycinena <alex.aycinena@gmail.com>
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
               Neil Williams <linux@codehelp.co.uk>

  Author:
               Chris Lyttle <chris@wilddev.net>
  Translators:
               Mechtilde STehmann <ooo@mechtilde.de></ooo>
-->

<chapter id="Reports">
  <title>Reports And Charts</title>

     <note><para>Dieser Abschnitt ist eine <quote>Baustelle</quote>. Ein
     Teil des Materials wurde noch nicht für V2.0 überprüft. Auch wenn es
     nicht ganz genau ist, ist es zumindest ein "Leitfaden".</para></note>

  <sect1 id="report-intro">
    <title>Einführung</title>

   <para>Berichte und Diagramme geben &app; die Möglichkeit, einen Überblick
   über Finanzdaten auf verschiedene Arten zu präsentieren. Dies kann von
   einer einfachen Zusammenfassung der Kontosummen bis hin zu einer erweiterten
   Portfolioansicht reichen. In diesem Abschnitt werden die wichtigsten &app;
   Berichte und deren Einstellung erläutert.</para>

   <para>Um einen Bericht oder ein Diagramm auszuführen, klicken Sie auf
   das Menü <menuchoice><guimenu>Berichte </guimenu></menuchoice> und wählen
   dann entweder einen Bericht aus (er wird mit den Standardoptionen geöffnet),
   oder Sie klicken auf <guibutton> Gespeicherte Berichtskonfiguration</guibutton>,
   um einen Bericht auszuwählen, den Sie zuvor konfiguriert und gespeichert
   haben.
   </para>

   <para>Wenn der Bericht geöffnet ist, klicken Sie auf die Schaltfläche
   <guibutton>Optionen</guibutton> in der Symbolleiste, um den Bericht
   nach Bedarf zu konfigurieren, z. B. um das Berichtsdatum einzustellen
   oder Konten auszuwählen.
   </para>

   <tip><para>Wenn Sie beabsichtigen, eine Berichtskonfiguration zu speichern,
   sollten Sie eine benannte Berichtsdatumsoption wie <emphasis>Heute</emphasis>
   wählen, anstatt ein bestimmtes Datum einzugeben, damit es nicht notwendig
   ist, in zukünftigen Berichten erneut ein bestimmtes Datum einzugeben.</para>
   </tip>

   <tip><para>Wenn Sie häufig einen Bericht mit einem Datum am Anfang oder
   Ende einer Abrechnungsperiode ausführen, stellen Sie das Start- und
   Enddatum der Abrechnungsperiode in <menuchoice><guimenu>Bearbeiten</guimenu>
   <guisubmenu>Einstellungen</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Abrechnungsperiode</guimenuitem>
   </menuchoice> ein und wählen Sie dann die entsprechenden Optionen für
   das Berichtsdatum.
       Siehe auch <xref linkend="prefs-accounting-period" />.
     </para>
   </tip>

   <tip>
     <para>Wenn Sie keinen bestimmten Bericht finden, der Ihren Anforderungen
     entspricht, können Sie eventuell den Assistenten <guilabel>Transaktion
     suchen</guilabel> (<menuchoice><guimenu>Bearbeiten</guimenu>
     <guimenuitem>Suchen</guimenuitem> </menuchoice>) verwenden, um eine
     Gruppe von Transaktionen auszuwählen, und diese dann mit <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Berichte</guimenu><guimenuitem>Kontobericht </guimenuitem>
       </menuchoice> auszugeben. Weitere Formatierungen oder Analysen können
       durch Kopieren und Einfügen des Berichts in eine Tabellenkalkulation
       vorgenommen werden.
     </para>
   </tip>

   <para>Nachdem Sie einen Bericht konfiguriert haben, können Sie die
   Konfiguration zur späteren Verwendung speichern, indem Sie entweder
   auf die Schaltfläche <guibutton>Berichtskonfiguration speichern</guibutton>
   oder <guibutton>Berichtskonfiguration speichern unter...</guibutton>
   klicken.
   </para>

   <sect2 id="report-saving">
     <title>Speichern einer Berichtskonfiguration</title>

     <para>Um eine Berichtskonfiguration für die zukünftige Verwendung zu
     speichern, gehen Sie, während die gewünschte Berichtsregisterkarte
     ausgewählt ist, zu den Berichtsoptionen, wählen Sie die Registerkarte
     <emphasis>Allgemein</emphasis> und ändern Sie den <emphasis>Berichtsnamen</emphasis>
     in einen aussagekräftigen, eindeutigen Namen. Verwechseln Sie dies
     nicht mit dem <emphasis>Berichtstitel</emphasis>, der oben in einem
     Bericht gedruckt wird.
     </para>

     <para>Klicken Sie auf die Schaltfläche <guibutton>Berichtskonfiguration
     speichern</guibutton> oder <guibutton>Berichtskonfiguration speichern
     unter...</guibutton>. Dadurch werden Ihre angepassten Berichtsoptionen
     in einer Datei in Ihrem Home-Verzeichnis gespeichert. Z.B. Linux:
     <emphasis>~/.gnucash/saved-reports-[versioninfo]</emphasis>
     </para>

     <para>Wenn Sie zum ersten Mal einen Report unter einem Namen speichern,
     der noch nicht gespeichert wurde, können Sie entweder die Schaltfläche
     <guibutton>Berichtskonfiguration speichern </guibutton> oder die Schaltfläche
     <guibutton>Berichtskonfiguration speichern unter... </guibutton> klicken.
     Sie können den Berichtsnamen vor dem Speichern ändern.
     </para>

     <para>Nachdem eine Berichtskonfiguration für einen bestimmten Namen
     gespeichert wurde, wird mit der Schaltfläche <guibutton>Berichtskonfiguration
     speichern</guibutton> die gespeicherte Berichtskonfiguration sofort
     aktualisiert, ohne dass die Möglichkeit besteht, die Konfiguration
     unter einem neuen Namen zu speichern. Verwenden
     Sie die Schaltfläche <guibutton>Berichtskonfiguration speichern
     unter...</guibutton>, um die aktuelle Berichtskonfiguration unter
     einem neuen Namen zu speichern.
     </para>

     <para>Nachdem Ihr benutzerdefinierter Bericht gespeichert wurde,
     steht er über das Menü <menuchoice><guimenu>Berichte</guimenu>
     <guimenuitem>Gespeicherte Berichtskonfigurationen</guimenuitem>
     </menuchoice> zur Verfügung und wird auch beim Start von <menuchoice>
       <guimenu>Berichte</guimenu><guisubmenu>Beispiel & Muster;
       Benutzerdefiniert</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Benutzerdefinierter
       mehrspaltiger Bericht</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
     </para>

   </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-working">
     <title>Arbeiten mit gespeicherten Berichtskonfigurationen</title>

     <para>Durch Auswahl von <menuchoice><guimenu>Berichte</guimenu>
     <guimenuitem>Gespeicherte Berichtskonfigurationen</guimenuitem>
     </menuchoice> wird ein Dialogfenster mit einer Liste der
     <emphasis>Gespeicherten Berichtskonfigurationen </emphasis> geöffnet,
     die Sie zuvor erstellt haben. Unter <emphasis>Gespeicherte
     Berichtskonfigurationen</emphasis> versteht man in diesem Zusammenhang
     den Satz der benutzerdefinierten Einstellungen für Standardreports.
     </para>

     <para>Das Fenster <emphasis>Gespeicherte Berichtskonfigurationen</emphasis>
     listet jede Ihrer zuvor gespeicherten Berichtskonfigurationen auf,
     sowie 3 kleine Schaltflächen am Ende jeder Konfiguration. Diese
     Schaltflächen führen die folgenden Aktionen aus
     </para>

     <itemizedlist>
       <listitem><para>Laden (und Ausführen) der Berichtskonfiguration.
       Ein Doppelklick auf eine Berichtskonfiguration führt auch diese
       Aktion aus.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem><para>Name der Berichtskonfiguration bearbeiten. Damit
       kann eine Berichtskonfiguration umbenannt werden.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem><para>Berichtskonfiguration löschen.</para>
       </listitem>

     </itemizedlist>

   </sect2>

  </sect1>

   <sect1 id="report-config">
      <title>Konfigurieren von Berichten und Diagrammen</title>

        <para>&app; Berichte haben viele Konfigurationsoptionen. Führen Sie
        zunächst den Originalbericht selbst aus. Rufen Sie dann die
        Berichtsoptionen mit der Schaltfläche <guibutton>Optionen</guibutton>
        in der Symbolleiste auf.</para>

           <note> <para>Geänderte Grafik-Engine-Optionen prüfen</para></note>

   <sect2 id="report-opt-btns">
     <title>Schaltflächen für Berichtsoptionen</title>

     <para>Nachdem Sie die Berichtsoptionen geändert haben, können Sie
     entweder
</para>

     <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
         <para>auf die Schaltfläche <guibutton>OK</guibutton> klicken, um die Änderungen zu übernehmen, den Bericht neu zu generieren und das
         Optionsfenster zu schließen.</para>

         <para>oder</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
         <para>auf die Schaltfläche <guibutton>Anwenden</guibutton> klicken,
          um die Änderungen zu übernehmen, den Bericht neu zu generieren
          und das Optionsfenster für mögliche weitere Änderungen offen zu
          lassen. In diesem Fall werden sowohl die Schaltflächen
          <guibutton>Anwenden</guibutton> als auch <guibutton>OK</guibutton>
          deaktiviert, was anzeigt, dass die Änderungen übernommen wurden,
          bis weitere Änderungen vorgenommen werden.

         </para>

         <para>oder</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
         <para>auf die Schaltfläche <guibutton>Abbrechen</guibutton> klicken,
         um das Optionsfenster zu schließen, ohne die noch nicht vorgenommenen
         Änderungen zu übernehmen.
       </listitem>
     </itemizedlist>

   </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-common">
     <title id="report-common.title">Allgemeine Berichtsoptionen</title>

        <para>Viele Berichte haben ähnliche Optionen. Einige häufige sind:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Berichtsname: Legen Sie den Titel des Berichts fest. Dies
            wird auch verwendet, um den Bericht zur späteren Ansicht zu
            drucken.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Datumsoptionen: Berichte geben normalerweise entweder
            ein einzelnes Datum oder einen Datumsbereich für den Bericht
            an. Datumsangaben können auf zwei Arten angegeben werden,
            entweder direkt (mit dem Datumsselektor) oder durch Auswahl
            eines relativen Datums aus dem Menü.Relative Datumsangaben
            ermöglichen die Angabe von Daten wie <guilabel>Anfang dieses
            Jahres</guilabel> oder <guilabel>Heute</guilabel>.</para>

            <tip><para>Wenn Sie häufig einen Bericht mit einem Datum am
            Anfang oder Ende einer Abrechnungsperiode ausführen, stellen
            Sie das Start- und Enddatum der Abrechnungsperiode in
            <menuchoice><guimenu>Bearbeiten</guimenu><guisubmenu>Einstellungen
            </guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Abrechnungsperiode </guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice> ein und wählen Sie dann die entsprechenden
            Optionen für das Berichtsdatum. Siehe <xref linkend="prefs-accounting-period" />.</para>
            </tip>

          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Schrittweite: Diese Option wird bei Balkendiagrammen
            verwendet, um das Intervall zu bestimmen, das jeder Balken
            darstellt. Typische Werte sind täglich, wöchentlich, monatlich
            und jährlich.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Konten: Wählen Sie die entsprechenden Konten für den
            Bericht aus. Beachten Sie, dass in einigen Berichten nur
            bestimmte Arten von Konten ausgewählt werden können. So
            können z. B. in einem Ausgabenkuchendiagramm nur
            Aufwandskonten ausgewählt werden. </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Lange Kontennamen anzeigen: Mit dieser Option können
            entweder kurze Kontennamen (z. B. Strom) oder lange
            Kontennamen (z. B. Nebenkosten:Strom) angezeigt werden.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Unterkonten einschließen?: Zusammenfassungsberichte haben
            in der Regel eine Option "Alle Unterkonten einschließen", die,
            wenn sie ausgewählt ist, sicherstellt, dass alle Unterkonten eingeschlossen werden, wenn das übergeordnete Konto eingeschlossen
            ist.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tiefe: Mit dieser Option können Sie auswählen, wie viele
            Ebenen der Bericht Unterkonten anzeigt. Wenn die Unterkonten
            tiefer gehen als ausgewählt, wird ein Gesamtwert für alle
            Unterkonten berechnet und in eine Summe einbezogen. Um
            sicherzustellen, dass jedes ausgewählte Konto einzeln angezeigt
            wird, wählen Sie <guibutton>Alle</guibutton>.</para>
          </listitem>
<!-- Please adapt the English part -->
          <listitem>
            <para>Formatvorlage: Wählen Sie eine Stilvorlage aus. Stilvorlagen steuern, wie Berichte angezeigt werden. Zurzeit gibt es vier
            Stilvorlagen: <guilabel>Voreinstellung</guilabel>,
            <guilabel>Einfach</guilabel>, <guilabel>Fußzeile</guilabel> und
            <guilabel>Bunt</guilabel>. Sie können jedes dieser Elemente über
            den Menüpunkt <menuchoice><guimenu>Bearbeiten</guimenu><guimenuitem>
            Stilvorlagen</guimenuitem></menuchoice> anpassen. Dies wird im
            Abschnitt <xref linkend="change-style"></xref><!--Ändern von
            Stilvorlagen--> beschrieben.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Diagrammabmessungen: Für die meisten Diagramme gibt es
            Optionen für Breite und Höhe, die die angezeigten Abmessungen
            (in Pixel) angeben).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Berichtswährung: Wählen Sie die Berichtswährung. In der
            Regel werden die Werte zur Anzeige in diese Währung
            umgerechnet.</para>

            <para>Die Standardberichtswährung wird in der Registerkarte
            <menuchoice> <guimenu>Bearbeiten</guimenu><guimenuitem>Einstellungen
            </guimenuitem></menuchoice> Berichte definiert.
            Siehe <xref linkend="prefs-reports" />.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Preisquelle: Wählen Sie aus, wie Aktien- und Währungspreise
            in diesem Bericht berechnet werden. Wählen Sie zwischen:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>Zeitlich nächstgelegen (Standard für die
              meisten Berichte): Ein Preis, der aus der Preisdatenbank
              an dem Datum abgerufen wurde, das dem Datum des Berichts
              oder des Datums für Zeitreihenberichte am nächsten liegt.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Aktuellste: Der letzte Preis in der
              Preisdatenbank.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Durchschnittskosten: Der betragsgewichtete
              <emphasis>Netto</emphasis>-Durchschnitt von
              <emphasis>allen</emphasis> Teilen, die die Wertpapiere
              gegen eine andere <emphasis>unabhängig vom Konto</emphasis>
              austauschen. Gewinn/Verlust-Aufteilungen werden <emphasis>in
              die Berechnung mit einbezogen</emphasis>.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>Gewichteter Durchschnitt: Der <emphasis>brutto
              </emphasis> betragsgewichtete Durchschnittspreis von
              <emphasis>allen</emphasis> Aufteilungen, die die Wertpapiere
              Gewinn-/Verlust-Aufspaltungen werden <emphasis>nicht</emphasis>
              in die Berechnung einbezogen.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            Weitere Informationen zu Durchschnittskosten und gewichtetem
            Durchschnitt finden Sie im Kapitel "Kapitalanlagen" des Handbuchs
            "Kurs und Konzepte".</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Summen: Diagramme zeigen Summen in der Diagrammlegende
            an, wenn diese Option ausgewählt ist.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Maximale Scheiben: Steuert die maximale Anzahl von Scheiben,
            die in einem Kreisdiagramm angezeigt werden - andere Konten
            werden in einer Scheibe mit der Bezeichnung Andere platziert.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Maximale Balken: Steuert die maximale Anzahl von Balken,
            die in einem Balkendiagramm angezeigt werden.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Spalten anzeigen: Wählen Sie die anzuzeigenden Spalten
            aus dem Register.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

   </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="report-classes">
   <title>Berichte nach Klasse aufgelistet</title>

   <para>&app; hat die Haupttypen von Berichte in Hauptklassen eingeteilt.
   Diese sind alle unter dem Menü Berichte verfügbar.</para>

     <sect2 id="report-general">
      <title>Allgemeine Berichte</title>

      <para>Zu den allgemeinen Berichten gehören der Kontenübersichtsbericht,
      die Zusammenfassung zukünftiger geplanter Buchungen, der
      Steuerbericht und <acronym> Elster</acronym>-Export sowie der
      Buchungsbericht und auch die Berichte im Menü Muster &amp; Beispiel;
       Benutzerdefiniert.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Kontenübersicht</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Zusammenfassung zukünftiger geplanter Buchungen</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="report-taxreport">
        <title>Steuer-Bericht und <acronym>Elster</acronym>-Export</title>
        <para>Der Steuer-Bericht listet alle steuerpflichtigen Einnahmen
        und abzugsfähigen Ausgabenbeträge auf, die bei der Erstellung der
         Einkommensteuererklärungen verwendet werden. Der Zweck des
         Berichts ist es, einen vollständigen Prüfpfad für diese Beträge
         bereitzustellen. Der Bericht soll von einem Steuerzahler verwendet
          werden, um seine eigene Steuererklärung manuell zu erstellen,
          oder er soll alternativ einem Steuerberater für diesen Zweck
          zur Verfügung gestellt werden. Der Bericht kann auch verwendet
          werden, um einen Export aller steuerlich relevanten Einnahmen
          und Ausgaben in eine <acronym>Elster</acronym>-Datei zu erzeugen
          (dies ist zusätzlich zum Export in das <acronym>HTML</acronym>-Format,
          das alle Berichte erlauben). Diese <acronym>Elster</acronym>-Datei
          kann in Steuererklärungsprogramme wie TaxCut oder TurboTax o.ä.
          importiert werden. Der Bericht sollte ausgeführt, sorgfältig
          auf Fehler oder Auslassungen geprüft und dann bei Bedarf Korrekturen
          an Buchungen, Berichtseinstellungen, Währungsumrechnungskursen
          oder der Kontenstruktur vorgenommen werden. Dieser Vorgang sollte
          so oft wie nötig wiederholt werden, bis alle Beträge im Bericht
          korrekt sind, bevor eine endgültige Version verwendet und
          zusammen mit den Steuererklärungen gespeichert wird.</para>

          <para> Für Konten, die in den Berichtsoptionen angegeben sind
          (keine = alle) und die auch als <guilabel>Steuerbezogen</guilabel>
          gekennzeichnet sind, werden alle Buchungen für den gewählten
          Zeitraum (ebenfalls in den Berichtsoptionen) einbezogen. Der
          Bericht sortiert Buchungen nach Datum innerhalb des Kontos
          und liefert Zwischensummen nach Konto innerhalb des
          Steuerkennzeichens innerhalb der Formular- oder
          Einteilungszeilennummer. Es werden auch Mehrfachkopien und
          Unterzeilen für ausgewählte Formulare/Schemata unterstützt.
           optional eine spezielle Datumsverarbeitung, um geschätzte
           Steuerzahlungen nach Jahresende einzubeziehen..</para>

          <para>Alle Summen sind in EUR angegeben, da dies die Währung
          ist, die für die Abgabe der Einkommenssteuererklärung erforderlich
          ist. Buchungsbeträge, die nicht in EUR sind, werden in EUR
          umgerechnet, indem der Umrechnungskurs für Buchungen in EUR
          verwendet wird, falls verfügbar. Ist dies nicht der Fall,
          wird ein Umrechnungskurs aus der Preisdatenbank verwendet
          (entweder das Datum, das dem Transaktionsdatum am nächsten
          liegt, oder das Datum, das dem Berichtsdatum am nächsten
          liegt, wie in den Berichtsoptionen angegeben; ist keines
          verfügbar, werden die Buchungsbeträge) auf Null umgerechnet
          und der Bericht enthält einen entsprechenden Kommentar. Es wird
          ein vollständiger Prüfpfad der Umrechnungen bereitgestellt.</para>

          <note><para>Damit dies funktioniert, muss der Benutzer
          steuerpflichtige und nicht steuerpflichtige Einkommen auf
          verschiedene Konten sowie abzugsfähige und nicht abzugsfähige
          Ausgaben aufteilen. Dazu wird der Dialog Einkommensteuerinformationen
          verwendet. Zum Dialog Einkommenssteuerinformationen gelangen
          Sie über <menuchoice><guimenu>Bearbeiten</guimenu><guimenuitem>
          Optionen Steuerbericht</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Der Benutzer
          muss auch die <acronym>Elster</acronym>-Kategorie jedes
          steuerbezogenen Kontos einstellen. Der Dialog
          Einkommensteuerinformationsdialog wird im Abschnitt
          <xref linkend="set-tax-options"></xref> beschrieben.</para></note>

      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Buchungsreport</title>

        <para>Dieser Bericht listet Buchungen in ausgewählten Konten
        während einer bestimmten Finanzperiode auf. Zwei Felder können
        optional zum Sortieren und Summieren verwendet werden.
        </para>

        <sect4 id="report-txrpt-opts">
          <title>Berichtsoptionen</title>

           <figure>
             <title><emphasis>Buchungsbericht, Berichtsoptionen</emphasis></title>
             <screenshot id="Help_TxRptOpt_Screen">
               <mediaobject>
                 <imageobject role="html">
                   <imagedata fileref="figures/Help_TxRptOpt_Screen.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Mechtilde Stehmann" width="510px"></imagedata>
                 </imageobject>

                 <imageobject role="fo">
                   <imagedata fileref="figures/Help_TxRptOpt_Screen.png" format="PNG"
                     srccredit="Mechtilde Stehmann" ></imagedata>
                 </imageobject>

                 <textobject><phrase>Buchungsbericht, Berichtsoptionen (Bild)</phrase>
                 </textobject>
                   <caption><para>Dies ist ein Bild des <emphasis>Buchungsberichts,
                   Berichtsoptionen, Registerkarte Anzeige.</emphasis></para>
                 </caption>
               </mediaobject>
             </screenshot>
           </figure>

           <itemizedlist>
             <listitem><para><emphasis>Accounts tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Accounts:</guilabel> Select one or more accounts to be reported.</para>
                   <para>There are 4 buttons to aid account selection</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Select All</entry><entry>Select all accounts</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Clear All</entry> <entry>Clear the selection and unselect all accounts</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Select Children</entry><entry>Select all descendants of selected account</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Select Default</entry><entry>Select the default account selection</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Hidden Accounts:</guilabel> Show accounts that have been marked hidden.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Filter By:</guilabel> Optionally select accounts to be either included or
                   excluded depending on Filter type</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Hidden Accounts:</guilabel> Show accounts that have been
                   marked hidden in the Filter By list of accounts</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Filter Type:</guilabel> One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>None</entry><entry>Do not do any filtering</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Include Transactions to/from Filter Accounts</entry>
                           <entry>Include Transactions to/from Filter Accounts only</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Exclude Transactions to/from Filter Accounts</entry>
                           <entry>Exclude Transactions to/from all Filter Accounts</entry>
                         </row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Reset defaults button:</guilabel> Reset all values to their defaults</para>
                 </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>

             </listitem>

             <listitem><para><emphasis>Display tab</emphasis></para>

               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Date</guilabel> refers to the 'posted date' i.e.
                 effective date of a transaction.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Reconciled Date</guilabel> refers to the 'date of
                 reconciliation' of a transaction.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Num</guilabel> is commonly used for check
                 numbers.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Description</guilabel> is a description of the transaction
                 </para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Memo</guilabel> is the memo field of a transaction. This
                 can be used as a secondary description of a transaction.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Notes:</guilabel> Display the notes if the memo is unavailable</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Account Name</guilabel> will print the account name
                 containing the transaction.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Use Full Account Name</guilabel> if the account name is
                 enabled, this option will display the full account name hierarchy.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Account Code</guilabel> this refers to the 'account code'
                 related to the account.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Detail Level</guilabel>&mdash; One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Single</entry><entry>Display 1 line</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Multi-Line</entry><entry>Display N lines</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                   <note>
                     <para>Before  stable version 3.0
                     <emphasis>Detail Level</emphasis> was called <emphasis>Style</emphasis> on the General tab.</para>
                   </note>

                   <para>If <emphasis>Detail Level</emphasis> is <emphasis>Multi-Line</emphasis>,
                     check boxes <emphasis>Other Account Name</emphasis> and <emphasis>Use Full Other Account Name</emphasis>
                     are automatically deselected and disabled, and the <emphasis>Transfer</emphasis> column is not reported.
                   </para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Other Account Name:</guilabel> For multi-split transactions, this parameter should be unticked. See below for more details.</para>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Use Full Other Account Name</guilabel> will enable
                 display of full corresponding account name.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Other Account Code</guilabel> will enable display of corresponding
                 account code.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Shares:</guilabel> Display number of shares</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Price:</guilabel> Display share prices</para></listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Amount:</guilabel> One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>None</entry><entry>Do not display Amount</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Single</entry><entry>Single column display</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Double</entry><entry>Two column display</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Subtotal Table</guilabel> will add a summary table
                 for the various subtotals generated in the report. It lists the same subtotals
                 generated in tabular form.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Running Balance</guilabel> refers to the running balance
                 of the account holding the transaction.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Totals</guilabel> will add a 'Grand Total' line
                 adding all transactions in the report.</para></listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Sign Reverses:</guilabel> One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Global Preference</entry><entry>Use reversing option specified in global preference.</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>None</entry><entry>Do not display signs reversed</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Credit Accounts</entry><entry>Reverse amount display for Liability, Payable, Equity, Credit Card and Income accounts</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Income and Expense</entry><entry>Reverse amount display for Income and Expense accounts</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Reset defaults button</guilabel> Reset all values to their defaults</para></listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>

             <listitem><para><emphasis>Filter tab</emphasis></para>
             <itemizedlist>
               <listitem><para><guilabel>Account Name Filter</guilabel> will include only selected accounts
               containing the substring. Alternatively, if the next option is checked, the account name
               filter will be matched according to full POSIX regular expressions.</para></listitem>
               <listitem><para><guilabel>Use regular expressions for account name filter</guilabel> toggles
               regular expressions for account name filter.</para></listitem>
               <listitem><para><guilabel>Transaction Filter</guilabel> will include only transactions
               which contain this substring in the description, notes, or memo. Alternatively if the
               next option is checked, the filter will be matched using full POSIX regular expressions.</para></listitem>
               <listitem><para><guilabel>Use regular expressions for transaction filter</guilabel> toggles
               regular expressions for the transaction filter.</para></listitem>
               <listitem><para><guilabel>Reconcile Status</guilabel></para>
               <informaltable>
                 <tgroup cols="2">
                   <tbody>
                     <row><entry>All</entry><entry>Show all transactions</entry></row>
                     <row><entry>Unreconciled</entry><entry>Unreconciled only</entry></row>
                     <row><entry>Cleared</entry><entry>Cleared only</entry></row>
                     <row><entry>Reconciled</entry><entry>Reconciled only</entry></row>
                   </tbody>
                 </tgroup>
               </informaltable>
               </listitem>
               <listitem><para><guilabel>Void Transactions:</guilabel> One of</para>
               <informaltable>
                 <tgroup cols="2">
                   <tbody>
                     <row><entry>Non-void only</entry><entry>Show only non-voided transactions</entry></row>
                     <row><entry>Void only</entry><entry>Show only voided transactions</entry></row>
                     <row><entry>Both</entry><entry>Show both and include voided transactions in totals</entry></row>
                   </tbody>
                 </tgroup>
               </informaltable>
               </listitem>
               <listitem><para><guilabel>Closing transactions:</guilabel> One of</para>
               <informaltable>
                 <tgroup cols="2">
                   <tbody>
                     <row><entry>Excluding closing transactions</entry><entry>Show only regular transactions</entry></row>
                     <row><entry>Show both closing and regular transactions</entry><entry>Show both regular and closing transactions</entry></row>
                     <row><entry>Show closing transactions only</entry><entry>Show closing transactions only</entry></row>
                   </tbody>
                 </tgroup>
               </informaltable>
               </listitem>
               <listitem><para><guilabel>Reset defaults button:</guilabel> Reset all values to their defaults</para></listitem>
             </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>

             <listitem><para><emphasis>General tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Report name:</guilabel> Enter a descriptive name for this report</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Stylesheet:</guilabel> Select Default, Easy, Footer or Technicolor</para></listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Start Date:</guilabel> Enter or select a specific Start Date</para>
                   <para>or   select one of the following named start date options which will be used to  determine the start date each time the report is run
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Today</entry><entry>The current date</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of this month</entry><entry>First day of the current month</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of previous month</entry><entry>First day of the previous month</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of current quarter</entry><entry>First day of the current quarterly accounting period</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of previous quarter</entry><entry>First day of the previous quarterly accounting period</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of this year</entry><entry>First day of the current calendar year</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of previous year</entry><entry>First day of the previous calendar year</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Start of accounting period</entry><entry>First day of the accounting period as defined in the global preferences</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>End Date:</guilabel> Enter or select a specific End Date,</para>
                 <para>or select one of the following named end date options which will be used to
                 determine the end date each time the report is run
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Today</entry><entry>The current date</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of this month</entry><entry>Last day of the current month</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of previous month</entry><entry>Last day of the previous month</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of current quarter</entry><entry>Last day of the current quarterly accounting period</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of previous quarter</entry><entry>Last day of the previous quarterly accounting period</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of this year</entry><entry>Last day of the current calendar year</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of previous year</entry><entry>Last day of the previous calendar year</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>End of accounting period</entry><entry>Last day of the accounting period as defined in the global preferences</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Style:</guilabel> One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Single</entry><entry>Display 1 line</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Multi-Line</entry><entry>Display N lines</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                   <note><para>In stable version 3.0, the <emphasis>Style</emphasis> option will be renamed to <emphasis>Detail Level</emphasis>
                     and moved to the Display tab.</para>
                   </note>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Common Currency:</guilabel> Convert all transactions into a common currency</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Report's currency:</guilabel> Select the currency to display values</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show original currency amount</guilabel> Also show original currency amounts</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Table for Exporting:</guilabel> Formats the table for cut &amp; paste exporting with extra cells</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Add options summary:</guilabel> Adds an informative text
                 describing options that were changed by user. This is mainly useful for
                 troubleshooting reports.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Reset defaults button:</guilabel> Reset all values to their defaults</para></listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>


               <listitem><para><emphasis>Sorting tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Primary Key:</guilabel> Primary Sort Key. One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>None</entry><entry>Do not sort</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Account Name</entry><entry>Sort and subtotal by account name</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Account Code</entry><entry>Sort and subtotal by account code</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Date</entry><entry>Sort by date</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Reconciled Date</entry><entry>Sort by the reconciled date</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Reconciled Status</entry><entry>Sort by the reconciled status</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Register Order</entry><entry>Sort as within the register</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Other Account Name</entry><entry>Sort by account transferred from/to's name</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Other Account Code</entry><entry>Sort by account transferred from/to's code</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Amount</entry><entry>Sort by amount</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Description</entry><entry>Sort by description</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Number</entry><entry>Sort by check/transaction number</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Memo</entry><entry>Sort by memo</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Primary Subtotal:</guilabel> Subtotal according to the primary key</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Primary Subtotal for Date Key:</guilabel> Do a date subtotal. Only configurable if primary key is date or reconciled date.
                   One of None, weekly, monthly, quarterly or yearly</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Primary Sort Order:</guilabel> One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Ascending</entry><entry>Smallest to largest, earliest to latest</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Descending</entry><entry>Largest to smallest, latest to earliest</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Secondary Key:</guilabel> Secondary Sort Key. Same options as Primary Key</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Secondary Subtotal:</guilabel> Subtotal according to the secondary key</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Secondary Subtotal for Date Key:</guilabel> Do a date subtotal. Only configurable if primary key is date or reconciled date.
                   One of None, weekly, monthly, quarterly or yearly</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Secondary Sort Order:</guilabel> One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Ascending</entry><entry>Smallest to largest, earliest to latest</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Descending</entry><entry>Largest to smallest, latest to earliest</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Full Account Name:</guilabel> Show the full account name for subtotals and subtitles</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Account Code:</guilabel> Show the account code for subtotals and subtitles</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Account Description:</guilabel> Show the account description for subtitles</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Informal Debit/Credit Headers:</guilabel> Show informal names for debit/credit
                 in the subtitles. This requires that subtotal is enabled, and the primary or sortkey is account or account code.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Add indenting columns:</guilabel> Add columns to align transactions within the same
                 grouping together, and can be useful to highlight groups.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show subtotals only (hide transactional data):</guilabel> Will hide transactions.
                 This may be useful for reports whereby only subtotals are required.</para></listitem>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Reset defaults button:</guilabel> Reset all values to their defaults</para></listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="report-txrpt-splits">
          <title>Displaying Split Account Details</title>
          <para>This is controled by the <emphasis>Detail Level</emphasis> option on the Display tab.</para>
          <note>
           <para>In stable versions before 3.0 this option was called <emphasis>Style</emphasis> on the General tab.</para>
          </note>
          <para>In <emphasis>Single</emphasis> line mode, there's only one line per transaction. So you can have
            the account name on one side of the equation and
          </para>

          <para>a. the other account name if there's only one other split in the transaction</para>

          <para>or</para>

          <para>b. "Split" if there are multiple other splits in the transaction. You can't
            display multiple "other" account names in one line. There's just no room for it.
          </para>

          <para>In the case of <emphasis>Multi-Line</emphasis> mode, this report uses a completely different concept.
            For each transaction, every split (both the split in this account and the
            split(s) in the other account(s) !) is printed on a separate line. And every
            split really means every split:  both the split which belongs in the account
            being reported and the split(s) in the other account(s) that balance the
            transaction. So even the most basic transaction, with only two splits (this
            account and other account) will print two lines in multiline mode.
          </para>

          <para>For a simple transaction like this</para>
          <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="4">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><emphasis>Description</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Account</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Debit</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Credit</emphasis></entry>
                </row>
                <row><entry>Cheques Received</entry></row>
                <row><entry>"multiple payers"</entry><entry>IncomeAccount</entry><entry></entry><entry>£30.00</entry></row>
                <row><entry></entry><entry>BankAccount</entry><entry>£30.00</entry><entry></entry></row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>

          <para>then on a Transaction Report for the bank account the details appear pretty much as above.</para>

          <para>For clarity of the accounts, you might enter transactions with multiple splits referring to the same
            account. For example, the above transaction might well be entered like this
          </para>

          <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="4">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry><emphasis>Description</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Account</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Debit</emphasis></entry>
                  <entry><emphasis>Credit</emphasis></entry>
                </row>
                <row><entry>Cheques Received</entry></row>
                <row><entry>"FirstPayer"</entry><entry>IncomeAccount</entry><entry></entry><entry>£10.00</entry></row>
                <row><entry>"SecondPayer"</entry><entry>IncomeAccount</entry><entry></entry><entry>£20.00</entry></row>
                <row><entry></entry><entry>BankAccount</entry><entry>£30.00</entry><entry></entry></row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>

          <para>When this transaction is printed on the bank account's Transaction Report in <emphasis>Single</emphasis> line mode, then
            under <emphasis>other account</emphasis> it simply prints the word <emphasis>split</emphasis> instead of the account name.
          </para>

          <para>To display the additional split detail, you need to set <emphasis>Single/Multi-Line</emphasis> to
            <emphasis>Multi-Line</emphasis> and then tick <emphasis>Display</emphasis> -> <emphasis>Account Name</emphasis>.
            Do NOT tick <emphasis>Display</emphasis> -> <emphasis>Other Account Name</emphasis>.
          </para>

          <para>You can choose whether or not to turn off the full account name using <emphasis>Display</emphasis> ->
            <emphasis>Use Full Account Name.</emphasis></para>

          <para><emphasis>Use Full Other Account Name</emphasis> has no effect in <emphasis>Multi-Line</emphasis> mode.</para>

        </sect4>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-assets">
    <title>Assets &amp; Liabilities</title>

     <para>The Assets &amp; Liabilities reports includes the Balance Sheet
       report, Investment reports and the Net Worth report.</para>

      <itemizedlist>

       <listitem>
        <para>Advanced Portfolio:</para>

        <para>Columns</para>
          <itemizedlist>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Account:</guilabel> Stock Account</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Symbol:</guilabel> Ticker Symbol/Abbreviation as defined in the Security Editor. A report option can suppress this column.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Listing:</guilabel> Type as defined in the Security Editor. A report option can suppress this column.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Shares:</guilabel> Number of shares (quantity). A report option sets how many decimal places to show.
      A report option can suppress this column.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Price:</guilabel> Unit market price as at report date. A report option can suppress this column.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Basis:</guilabel> Cost of all shares acquired by any means, including brokerage fees if the option to include them is checked. Report option <emphasis>Basis calculation method</emphasis> can be set to Average, LIFO or FIFO.</para>
      </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Value:</guilabel> Number of shares * Unit market price as at report date</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Money In:</guilabel> Sum of the cost of stock purchased, excluding stock acquired as part of a Dividend Reinvestment Plan. I.e. External money used to purchase shares.</para>
      </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Money Out:</guilabel> Money from selling shares or a spin off transaction.</para>
      </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Realized Gain:</guilabel> Money received for selling shares minus basis for shares sold, minus brokerage fees for the sale if the option to include them in basis is checked.</para>
      </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Unrealized Gain:</guilabel> Value less Basis for unsold shares</para>
      </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Total Gain:</guilabel> Realized Gain + Unrealized Gain</para>
      </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Rate of Gain:</guilabel> Total Gain / Money In * 100 (from &app; 2.6.1 onwards)</para>
      </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Income:</guilabel> Total of all income transactions associated with a stock account.</para>
              <note>
                <para>To include income from dividends which are not reinvested (if there is no split to the stock account in the income transaction, the report has no way of associating the income with a particular stock) :
                </para>
    <para>Ensure there is a dummy transaction split to the stock         account with quantity 0, price 1 and value 0 in the dividend transaction. Enter the dummy stock split with no values in the dividend account and it will create the transaction with price 1 even though you cannot see the Price column in that register.
    </para>
                <para>In GnuCash 2.6.6, this report was modified to simplify the recording of dividend and interest payments. With this
                change it may not be necessary to include the dummy stock split in the transaction. The report will find income (and expense) transactions that are in the parent account of the stock account being reported on. This is done by looking in the parent account for transactions that have exactly two splits (not counting trading account splits) where the other split is to an income or expense account with the same name as the stock's account.
                </para>
                <para>For example given an account structure like
                </para>
                <literallayout>
                Assets (type ASSET)
                  Broker (type ASSET)
                    Widget Stock (type STOCK)
                Income (type INCOME)
                  Dividends (type INCOME)
                    Widget Stock (type INCOME)
                </literallayout>
                <para>A transaction that debits the "Assets:Broker" account and credits the "Income:Dividends:Widget Stock" account will count as income even though it doesn't have a split with account "Assets:Broker:Widget Stock".
                </para>
                <para>This only works if the parent account ("Assets:Broker" in this case) is a Bank or Asset account and the Income/Expense account has the same name as the stock account. It won't double count transactions that have a dummy split since they won't have exactly two split transactions.
                </para>
                <para>It will not work if the income or expense account split is to a subaccount of the account with the same name as the stock account i.e. "Income:Dividends:Widget Stock:Franked"
                </para>
        </note>
      </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Brokerage Fees:</guilabel> Brokerage Fees</para>
      </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Total Return:</guilabel> Total Gain + Income</para>
      </listitem>

            <listitem><para><guilabel>Rate of Return:</guilabel> Total Return / Money In * 100</para>
      </listitem>

          </itemizedlist>

        <para>Common report options are described in <xref linkend="report-config"/></para>

        <para>Report Specific Options</para>

        <itemizedlist>  <!-- list of Tabs -->

          <listitem><para>Accounts Tab</para>

            <itemizedlist>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Include accounts with no shares:</guilabel> Unchecked (default) or checked.</para>
              </listitem>

            </itemizedlist>

          </listitem>  <!-- end of Accounts Tab -->

          <listitem><para>Display Tab</para>

            <itemizedlist>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Show ticker symbols:</guilabel> Checked (default) or unchecked. If unchecked, Symbol column will be omitted.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Show listings:</guilabel> Checked (default) or unchecked. If unchecked, Listing column (source of shares price quotes) will be omitted.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Show number of shares:</guilabel> Checked (default) or unchecked. If unchecked, Shares column will be omitted.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Share decimal places:</guilabel> The number of decimal places to show in the number of shares. Default is 2.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Show prices:</guilabel> Checked (default) or unchecked. If unchecked, Price column will be omitted.</para>
              </listitem>

            </itemizedlist>

          </listitem>  <!-- end of Display Tab -->

          <listitem><para>General Tab</para>

            <itemizedlist>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Price Source:</guilabel> Nearest in time (default) or Most Recent.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Basis calculation method:</guilabel> Average (default), FIFO or LIFO.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>Set preference for price list data:</guilabel> Checked (default): Use price list data. If there is no relevant price list data, transaction prices will be used and there will be a warning. Unchecked: Get prices from stock transactions.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem><para><guilabel>How to report brokerage fees:</guilabel> Include in basis (default), Include in gain or Ignore.</para>
              </listitem>

            </itemizedlist>

          </listitem>

        </itemizedlist>

       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Asset Barchart:</para>

        <para>The Asset Barchart report displays bars that present the value of all assets in a
        &app; file over time.  By default, the report shows all accounts
        in <emphasis>Accounts Receivable</emphasis>, <emphasis>Current Assets</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>Fixed Assets</emphasis>, <emphasis>Investments</emphasis> and Special Accounts
        (if they exist) and it displays monthly bars for the current financial period.
        This report provides a graphic view of the assets in the file over time.</para>

        <tip>
          <para>Like all the generic reports, the user can assign a title and save the report with
          it's selected options for re-use later.</para>
        </tip>

        <para>The display is in the form of either a stacked barchart or simple barchart with an
        option to display a table of the values.</para>

        <para>This report calculates and displays a default of 8 bars or up to 24 separate asset
        accounts value at the end of the day on several dates through a specified time period.
        The report automatically selects the most significant accounts to display with all other
        selected accounts summed as <emphasis>Other</emphasis>.</para>

        <para>The report exploits the outline structure of the chart of accounts to allow the user
        to select top level accounts and sub-accounts down to a user-selectable depth.  Selected
        sub-accounts below the selected depth are automatically <emphasis>summed up</emphasis> into
        the next level when it is also selected.  The default number of sub-account levels is 2,
        giving a summary view.  Increasing the number of sub-levels increases the detail available
        to display. It is possible to un-select a higher level account and leave sub-accounts
        selected to force greater detail to appear in the report.</para>

        <para>By default the report includes all <emphasis>asset</emphasis> accounts and sub-accounts,
        as well as <emphasis>Imbalance</emphasis> and <emphasis>Orphan</emphasis> Special accounts
        in whatever currencies or commodities may be present. The report's base currency is the
        default currency of the &app; file but if the file has data
        for multiple currencies, then it can be changed to another currency.</para>

        <para>Since each account may be individually selected, the report can be designed to focus
        on a small subset of data such as current assets or investments.</para>

        <para>The overall interval of the report defaults to start at the start of the current
        accounting period and to end at the end of the current accounting period. Numerous
        other starting choices and ending choices are available.</para>

        <para>The first bar shows the selected values at the end of the day on the first date chosen.
        There are a number of choices for step size from <emphasis>day</emphasis> to
        <emphasis>year</emphasis> with the default being <emphasis>month</emphasis>. Note that if any
        step date would fall on the 29th, 30th or 31st in a month that does not have such a date
        the next interval will be 31 days later. For that step only the date will <emphasis>slip</emphasis>
        up to 3 days into the following month. This is true for releases at least through 2.4.13.
        Bug 639049 is open in Bugzilla to modify this behavior.</para>

        <para>Currently, there is no option to start the report on the last day of any period.
        There is also no option to show <emphasis>beginning</emphasis> balances or <emphasis>end of
        previous step</emphasis> balances. This makes it difficult to correlate this report to
        business quarterly reports, for example.</para>

        <para>The Net Worth linechart report, Liability barchart report and Net Worth barchart
        report are similar except for the graphic type and default account groups selected.</para>

       <para>Other features are customizable in a manner similar to other standard reports.</para>

       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Asset Piechart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Average Balance:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Balance Sheet: This report summarizes assets, liabilities, and equity.
         When properly maintained, assets should equal the sum of liabilities and equity.
         If that is not the case, there is some kind of internal imbalance in the
         accounts.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Balance Sheet using eguile-gnc:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>General Journal:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>General Ledger:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Investment Portfolio: This report summarizes the value of the stocks in
         the current portfolio.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Liability Barchart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Liability Piechart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Net Worth Barchart: Net worth is the difference between the value of assets
         or liabilities.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Net Worth Linechart: Net worth plotted over time.  Net worth is the difference between the value of assets
         or liabilities.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Price Scatterplot:</para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

   </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-biz">
    <title>Business Reports</title>

      <para>The Business Reports includes Customer and Vendor Reports and Printable
       Invoices as well as Aging reports.</para>

       <sect3>
        <title>Customer Report</title>
        <para> </para>
       </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Customer Summary</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Easy Invoice</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Employee Report</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Fancy Invoice</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Job Report</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Payable Aging</title>
         <para>This report provides a listing of vendors and their aged
           outstanding balances. Vendors may be included if they have posted
           business transactions (e.g. invoices) for the selected accounts payable
           account. It shows their current balance, and how much they have
           due from invoices over time periods 0-30 days, 31-60 days,
           61-90 days, and over 90 days. The report also contains links to each
           vendor and to their current vendor report.
         </para>
         <para>Optionally, vendor address details may be also shown.</para>

         <tip><para>To export vendor address details, say in order to do a mail
           merge, select the optional vendor address details in the report options
           display tab, apply the options to regenerate the report, then copy and
           paste the report into a spreadsheet. Alternatively, the report can be
           exported to a .html file, then read into a spreadsheet.</para>
         </tip>

         <sect4 id="report-pay-aging-opts">
           <title>Report Options</title>

           <note><para>See
             <link linkend='report-common' endterm="report-common.title"/> in the
             <emphasis>Configuring Reports and Charts</emphasis> section of this
             help manual for more details of the common options.
             </para>
           </note>

           <itemizedlist>
             <listitem><para><emphasis>General tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel> Report name:</guilabel>
                   Enter a descriptive name for this report - see
                   <link linkend='report-common' endterm="report-common.title"/>.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Stylesheet:</guilabel>
                   Select a style sheet for this report - see
                   <link linkend='report-common' endterm="report-common.title"/>.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>To:</guilabel> Select a date
                   to report on or a named date. Transactions up to and
                   including the selected date will be used to calculate the
                   outstanding aged balances. See
                   <link linkend='report-common' endterm="report-common.title"/>.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Report's currency:</guilabel>
                   Select the currency to display the values in - see
                   <link linkend='report-common' endterm="report-common.title"/></para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Price Source:</guilabel>
                   Select the source of price information used for currency
                   conversion if needed. One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Average Cost</entry><entry>The
                           volume-weighted net average price of all exchanges.</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Weighted Average (default)</entry><entry>
                           The volume-weighted gross average price of all exchanges up to the date of the report</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Most recent</entry><entry>The most recent
                           recorded price</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Nearest in time</entry><entry>The price
                           recorded nearest in time to the report date</entry>
                         </row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Multi-currency Totals:</guilabel>
                   If not selected, all totals are shown in the report
                   currency.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Sort By:</guilabel> Sort
                   companies by one of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Name (default)</entry><entry>Company name
                           </entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Total Owed</entry><entry>Total amount owed
                           to company</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Bracket Total Owed</entry><entry>Amount
                           owed in oldest bracket. If same, use next oldest
                           </entry>
                         </row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Sort Order:</guilabel> One of
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Increasing (default)</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Decreasing</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show zero balance items:</guilabel>
                   Show companies even if they have a zero outstanding
                   balance.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Due or Post Date:</guilabel>
                   Leading date. Which date to use to determine aging. One of
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Due Date (default)</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Post Date</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Payable Account:</guilabel>
                   The accounts payable account used to select vendors to be
                   reported. Vendors are included if they have a posted
                   business transaction (usually an invoice) on or before the
                   report date and also meet the <emphasis>Show zero balance
                   items</emphasis> criteria.</para>
                 </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>

             <listitem><para><emphasis>Display tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address Name:</guilabel>
                   Display vendor address name. This, and other fields, may be
                   useful if copying this report to a spreadsheet for use in a
                   mail merge.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 1:</guilabel> Display
                   address line 1.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 2:</guilabel> Display
                   address line 2.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 3:</guilabel> Display
                   address line 3.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 4:</guilabel> Display
                   address line 4.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Phone:</guilabel> Display
                   address phone number.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Fax:</guilabel> Display
                   address fax number.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Email:</guilabel> Display
                   email address.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Active:</guilabel> Display
                   vendor active status.</para>
                 </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
         </sect4>

        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Printable Invoice</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Receivable Aging</title>
         <para>This report provides a listing of customers and their aged
           outstanding balances. Customers may be included if they have posted
           business transactions (e.g. invoices) for the selected accounts receivable
           account. It shows their current balance, and how much they have
           outstanding from invoices over time periods 0-30 days, 31-60 days,
           61-90 days, and over 90 days. The report also contains links to each
           customer and to their current customer report.
         </para>
         <para>Optionally, customer address details may be also shown.</para>

         <tip><para>To export customer address details, say in order to do a mail
           merge, select the optional customer address details in the report options
           display tab, apply the options to regenerate the report, then copy and
           paste the report into a spreadsheet. Alternatively, the report can be
           exported to a .html file, then read into a spreadsheet.</para>
         </tip>

         <sect4 id="report-rec-aging-opts">
           <title>Report Options</title>

           <note><para>See
             <link linkend='report-common' endterm="report-common.title"/> in the
             <emphasis>Configuring Reports and Charts</emphasis> section of this
             help manual for more details of the common options.
             </para>
           </note>

           <itemizedlist>
             <listitem><para><emphasis>General tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel> Report name:</guilabel>
                   Enter a descriptive name for this report - see
                   <link linkend='report-common' endterm="report-common.title"/>.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Stylesheet:</guilabel>
                   Select a style sheet for this report - see
                   <link linkend='report-common' endterm="report-common.title"/>.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>To:</guilabel> Select a date
                   to report on or a named date. Transactions up to and
                   including the selected date will be used to calculate the
                   outstanding aged balances. See
                   <link linkend='report-common' endterm="report-common.title"/>.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Report's currency:</guilabel>
                   Select the currency to display the values in - see
                   <link linkend='report-common' endterm="report-common.title"/>.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Price Source:</guilabel>
                   Select the source of price information used for commodity
                   conversion if needed. One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Average Cost</entry><entry>The
                           volume-weighted net average price of all exchanges</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Weighted Average (default)</entry><entry>
                           The volume-weighted gross average price of all exchanges</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Most recent</entry><entry>The most recent
                           recorded price</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Nearest in time</entry><entry>The price
                           recorded nearest in time to the report date</entry>
                         </row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show Multi-currency Totals:</guilabel>
                   If not selected, all totals are shown in the report
                   currency.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Sort By:</guilabel> Sort
                   companies by one of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Name (default)</entry><entry>Company name
                           </entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Total Owed</entry><entry>Total amount owed
                           by company</entry>
                         </row>
                         <row><entry>Bracket Total Owed</entry><entry>Amount
                           owed in oldest bracket. If same, use next oldest
                           </entry>
                         </row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Sort Order:</guilabel> One of
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Increasing (default)</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Decreasing</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Show zero balance items:</guilabel>
                   Show companies even if they have a zero outstanding
                   balance.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Due or Post Date:</guilabel>
                   Leading date. Which date to use to determine aging. One of
                   </para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Due Date (default)</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Post Date</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Receivables Account:</guilabel>
                   The accounts receivable account used to select customers to be
                   reported. Customers are included if they have a posted
                   business transaction (usually an invoice) on or before the
                   report date and also meet the <emphasis>Show zero balance
                   items</emphasis> criteria.</para>
                 </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>

             <listitem><para><emphasis>Display tab</emphasis></para>
               <itemizedlist>
                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address Source:</guilabel>
                   Which customer address fields to display. One of</para>
                   <informaltable>
                     <tgroup cols="2">
                       <tbody>
                         <row><entry>Billing (default)</entry><entry>Address fields from
                           billing address.</entry></row>
                         <row><entry>Shipping</entry><entry>Address fields from
                           shipping address.</entry></row>
                       </tbody>
                     </tgroup>
                   </informaltable>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address Name:</guilabel>
                   Display customer address name. This, and other fields, may be
                   useful if copying this report to a spreadsheet for use in a
                   mail merge.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 1:</guilabel> Display
                   address line 1.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 2:</guilabel> Display
                   address line 2.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 3:</guilabel> Display
                   address line 3.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Address 4:</guilabel> Display
                   address line 4.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Phone:</guilabel> Display
                   address phone number.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Fax:</guilabel> Display
                   address fax number.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Email:</guilabel> Display
                   email address.</para>
                 </listitem>

                 <listitem><para><guilabel>Active:</guilabel> Display
                   vendor active status.</para>
                 </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             </listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
         </sect4>

        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Tax Invoice</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
         <title>Vendor Report</title>
         <para> </para>
        </sect3>

     </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-income">
    <title>Income &amp; Expense</title>

     <para>The Income &amp; Expense reports includes the Cash Flow and Income Statement reports.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>Cash Flow:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Equity Statement:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Expense Barchart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Expense Piechart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Expense vs Day of Week:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Income &amp; Expense Chart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Income Barchart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Income Piechart:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Income Statement: This report summarizes sources of income and expenditure.
         (This report was called Profit &amp; Loss in gnucash-1.8.)</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Income vs Day of Week:</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Profit &amp; Loss: This is the same report as the Income Statement but with a different title.</para>
       </listitem>

       <listitem>
        <para>Trial Balance: This report summarizes sources of income and expenditure.</para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

   </sect2>

    <sect2 id="report-sample">
      <title>Sample &amp; Custom</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Welcome Sample Report</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Custom Multicolumn Report</title>
        <para>This report is used to place multiple reports
           into a single report window to examine a set of financial information at a glance.
        </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Sample Report with Examples</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

   </sect2>

   <sect2 id="report-budget">
     <title>Budget</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Balance Sheet</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Barchart</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Flow</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Income Statement</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Profit &amp; Loss</title>
        <para> </para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Budget Report</title>
  <para>This report is used to compare budgeted and real amounts for selected accounts. It allows you to review how well you follow the budget.</para>
  <para>The report is generated as a table in which each row represents an account and each set of columns shows the <emphasis>budgeted amount</emphasis>, the <emphasis>real amount</emphasis>, and the <emphasis>difference</emphasis> between them for each report period.</para>
  <para>Each entry in the <emphasis>real amount</emphasis> column is the sum of all the splits in the row's account over the column's period. For example, if the report is set up for monthly periods, the column is for May, and the row is for Expenses:Groceries, then the value will be the sum of all Expenses:Groceries splits for that May.</para>
  <para>The report supports selecting a range of periods instead all of them. Periods that are out of range can be included in the report as the consolidated columns around the selected range. This allows you to focus on particular periods, for example the current one, and is especially useful for budgets with many periods. For example, if you have a 12 period budget you can make a 3 column report with the format "(all periods before columns set) (current period columns set) (all periods after columns set)" that is easily fits on the screen and allows you to match values with account names.</para>
  <para><emphasis>Budget report options</emphasis></para>
  <para>
    <note><para>Here we describe only options that are specific for the Budget Report. You can find information about standard parameters in <xref linkend="report-config"/>.</para> </note>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Show budget</emphasis> - include the budgeted values for the period</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Show actual</emphasis> - include the real values for the period</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Show difference</emphasis> - include the difference between budgeted and real values for the period. Enabling this option does not force including budgeted and actual values in the report</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Show Column with totals</emphasis> - Adds a final column set containing budgeted, real value, and difference columns summing those values across all periods of the report.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Rollup budget amounts to parent</emphasis> - not used in the report, can be deleted or should be fixed</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Include accounts with zero total balances and budget values</emphasis> - enables display of accounts with no budget or splits in any period.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Budget</emphasis> - Select the budget to use for report generation</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Report for range of budget periods</emphasis> - Enables reporting on a subset of the budget by selecting a beginning and an ending period.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Range start</emphasis> - a combobox with a list of options to select the start period:
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>First</emphasis> - select first budget period</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Previous</emphasis> - select previous period.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Current</emphasis> - select current period.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Next</emphasis>  - select next period.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Last</emphasis> - select last budget period</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Manual</emphasis> - enables spinbox where you can select exact period</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>
      <note><para>The <emphasis>current</emphasis>, <emphasis>previous</emphasis>, and <emphasis>next</emphasis> options select the period based on the date on which the report is run, with <emphasis>current</emphasis> being the period in which the date falls, <emphasis>previous</emphasis> being the one before that, and <emphasis>next</emphasis> the period after. If the current date falls outside the date range covered by the budget, the <emphasis>first</emphasis> or <emphasis>last</emphasis> period will be used as appropriate.</para></note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Exact start period</emphasis> - options for select exact start period, enabled only if the range start option is set to <emphasis>Manual</emphasis></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Range end</emphasis> - a combobox with a list of options to select the end period. Values are the same as in <emphasis>Range start</emphasis> options</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Exact end period</emphasis> - the same as <emphasis>Exact start period</emphasis> but for the end of range</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Include collapsed periods before selected</emphasis> - if on, then includes in the report all budget periods, that are before selected period range, as a single consolidated column set</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis>Include collapsed periods after selected</emphasis> - if on, then includes in the report all budget periods, that are after selected period range, as a single consolidated column set.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

   </sect1>

   <sect1 id="report-print">
     <title>Printing or Exporting Reports and Charts</title>

       <note><para> Verify !!!  How customize printing with Gnome?</para></note>

     <para>&app; is able to print reports and to export the reports to <acronym>HTML</acronym> (web) pages. The
       Print &app; Document dialog is accessed from the <guibutton>Print</guibutton> button on the <emphasis>Toolbar</emphasis> or
       go to <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Print</guimenuitem></menuchoice> in the menu. To Export a report to a web page (<acronym>HTML</acronym>) select
       the <guibutton>Export</guibutton> button on the <emphasis>Toolbar</emphasis> and type in a file name.</para>

     <para>Most reports, being presented in HTML, can also be copied and pasted into a spreadsheet.</para>

     <para>The Print &app; Document dialog is used to select which Printer to send the
       print job to or to print to a File. It also contains a Preview button to view the
       document before printing. Press Print to send the job to the selected printer or
       <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> to dismiss the Print dialog.</para>


       <para>Printing from an open register prints the Account Report, which is also called
         the Register Report. This lists transactions in the account with a total. Other
         reports print as viewed in the Report screen.</para>
   </sect1>

  <sect1 id="report-create">
    <title>Creating Reports and Charts</title>

    <note><para>This section may need updating !!!</para> </note>

     <para>It is possible to write reports if the current ones are not suitable. To do this
       you will need to know Scheme (a LISP-like programming language), and it is an
       excellent idea to have a copy of the &app; source code available. </para>

     <para>The reporting interface is documented in the source code file
       <filename>src/report/report-system/doc/report-html.txt</filename>.
       The file <filename>src/report/utility-reports/hello-world.scm</filename>
       in the &app; source distribution provides a
       good example of how reports are developed.</para>

    <sect2 id="report-api">
      <title>Accessing the &app; <acronym>API</acronym></title>

      <para>It is also necessary to access data from the engine to get
        information for your report. This is
        <emphasis>since version 2.1.x</emphasis> performed by a set of
        Scheme wrapper functions that are documented in the file
        <filename>src/engine/swig-engine.c</filename>.
        <emphasis>Up to version 2.0.5</emphasis> it was
        <filename>src/g-wrap/gnc.html</filename>. Examine some of the other
        reports in src/scm/report for an indication of how they are used.</para>

      <para>Some users started a table in <ulink url="&url-wiki-api-custom;" />.</para>

      <para>Because the above file only contains the syntax of the function
        you can use the Doxygen source documentation either local after running
<screen>
./configure --enable-doxygen --enable-html-docs
make doc
</screen> on your sources or online
       <ulink url="&url-doc-api-main;" /> or
       <ulink url="&url-doc-api-mast;" />
       to get more information about the functions.
     </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="report-render">
    <title>Berichtsdarstellung</title>
    <para>Derzeit werden Berichte durch den Aufruf einer
    <acronym>HTML</acronym>-Generierungs-API erzeugt, die einen Dialekt
    von <acronym>HTML</acronym> ausgibt und diesen mit einem
    <acronym>HTML</acronym>-Widget darstellt. Dies hat Einschränkungen,
    insbesondere wenn man versucht, Objekte präzise auszurichten, wie
    es z. B. für den Druck auf vorgedruckte Rechnungen notwendig sein
    könnte.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

</chapter>
